{
  "reference_number": "10249",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I targeting negative levels of CO2 and other long-lived gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I believe the circumstances requiring a change would need to be significant changes in international politics or technology - and that\n\n would significant enough to warrant a full repeal of the bill"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n setting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\n circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\n\n economy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\n circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\n supplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy. The government should also consider intergenerational equity, and do\n\n this by not discounting action now because of perceived future economic growth. The government should also consider the impact\nof climate change on pacific peoples."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be thorough, and balanced enough to not leave vulnerable\n\nmembers of the community behind. They may affect certain industries more than others, and this is OK providing the government\ndoes what it can to facilitate a transition pathway for those industries. The plans should also reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o\n\nWaitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • Te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\n\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI think expertise in public health is also important, and representation for pacific peoples."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\n\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
